Guide to the Maurice Shapiro Environmental Health Collection, 1919-2001 UA.90.F65
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Research Files, 1919-2000; IV.
  - Water, 1930-2000; 12.
    - Report on a Special Study of the Assignment of Water Supply and Water Pollution Control Functions in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1965 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Report to the Surgeon General on the Health Aspects of Water, 1965 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Research, 1976-1980 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Risk Assessment Project Executive Summary and Recommendations, undated (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - River quality, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - River studies, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - River Study Center, 1972-1976 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Safe Drinking Water Act, 1978-1986 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Sanitary Survey of the McKeesport Water Treatment Plant by Allegheny County Health Department, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Science, Voters, and the Fluoridation Controversy, undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Selected Analysis and Monitoring of Lake Erie Water Quality, 1972-1973 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Selected Analysis and Monitoring of Lake Erie Water Quality, 1974 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Setting the Course: Clean Water, undated (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Sierra Club, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Source Book for Industrial Water Pollution Compliance Program, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission, 1975-1977 (Box 36, Folder 17)
    - State Water Plan, 1974-1982 (Box 36, Folder 18-20)
    - Status of Flood-Plain Mapping, Greater Pittsburgh Region, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 21)
    - A Study on the Nature of Noncompliance with Pennsylvania Clean Streams Law, 1970 (Box 36, Folder 22)
    - A System Analysis Model for Calculating Radionuclide Transport between Receiving Waters and Bottom Sediments, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 23)
    - Task Group on Drinking Water and Waste Water, 1981 (Box 36, Folder 24)
    - Techniques for the Assessment of the Carcinogenic Risk to the U.S. Population due to Exposure from Selected Volatile Organic Compounds from Drinking Water via the Ingestion, Inhalation and Dermal Routes, 1984 (Box 36, Folder 25)
    - Total Exposure to Volatile Organic Compounds in Potable Water, 1988 (Box 36, Folder 26)
    - Toward a National Water Plan, undated (Box 36, Folder 27)
    - Trace element sampling, 1968 (Box 36, Folder 28)
    - Trace Metal Study, 1968 (Box 36, Folder 29)
    - Transformation of Deterministic and Stochastic Processes in Hydrology, 1967 (Box 36, Folder 30)
    - Treatment Processes for Coping with Variation in Raw Water Quality, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 31)
    - Universities Council on Water Resources Newsletter, 1969-1971 (Box 36, Folder 32)
    - University-wide environmental effort, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 33)
    - Water control, 1956-1963 (Box 36, Folder 34)
    - Water hardness and health, 1960-1985 (Box 36, Folder 35)
    - Water management, 1983-1988 (Box 36, Folder 36)
    - Water: Our Number 1 Natural Resources Problem, undated (Box 36, Folder 37)
    - Water pollution, 1988-1991 (Box 36, Folder 38)
    - Water Quality Assessment, 1992 (Box 36, Folder 39)
    - Water Quality Committee, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 40)
    - Water Quality in Impoundments and Modifications from Destratification, 1967 (Box 36, Folder 41)
    - Water Quality Management, 1987 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Water Quality in Open Finished Water Reservoirs, undated (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Water Research Centre, 1980 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Water Resource Development and Management in the Tucson Basin, 1968 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Water Supply Engineering, 1951 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Water supply problems, 1980 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Water supply and sanitation in developing countries, 1966-1967 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Water treatment, 1967-1981 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Water viruses, undated (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Water and Wastewater Technology, 1968-1970 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Water for the World, undated (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Watershed tables, undated (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Westinghouse, undated (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Workshop on Federal Water Pollution Control Act Amendments, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Volatile Synthetic Organic Chemicals in Drinking Water, 1986 (Box 37, Folder 15)
- University of Pittsburgh Files, 1946-1999; V.
  The University of Pittsburgh Files Series contains material related to Shapiro's career as a professor at the University of Pittsburgh. The series contains four subseries: Administrative Material; Course Material; Presentations and Publications; and Student Papers. The material in this series dates from 1946 to 1999, though the bulk of the material is from his tenure as professor between 1951 and 1982. The series is arranged alphabetically, and includes papers, correspondence, reports, memos, publications, the text of presentations, and syllabi.
  - Administrative Material, 1949-1999; 1.
    - Academic Manual, 1976 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Accreditation, 1968-1969 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Accreditation, 1977 (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - Accreditation, 1980 (Box 37, Folder 19-20)
    - Accreditation, 1980-1981 (Box 37, Folder 21)
    - Accreditation, 1985 (Box 37, Folder 22-23)
    - Association of Schools of Public Health, 1984-1987 (Box 37, Folder 24)
    - Association of Teachers of Environmental Health, 1981-1984 (Box 37, Folder 25)
    - Board of Visitors, 1968-1988 (Box 37, Folder 26)
    - Budget, 1957 (Box 37, Folder 27)
    - Center for Environmental and Occupational Health, undated (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Conference Materials, 1971-1990 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Council on Education for Public Health, 1986-1988 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Curriculum, 1952-1960 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Curriculum, 1960-1968 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Curriculum, 1968-1993 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Curriculum, 1993 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Cooperation with Allegheny County Health Department, 1987 (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Deans' Interviews, undated (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Dedication ceremony, 1957 (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - Department of Environmental and Occupational Health, 1967-1994 (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Department of Epidemiology, 1981 (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Department Heads' Meetings, 1973-1984 (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Department of Public Health Practice, 1963 (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - Education for Environmental Protection, undated (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - Educational Policy, 1956 (Box 38, Folder 17)
    - Emergency Response Planning, undated (Box 38, Folder 18)
    - Environmental Health Council, 1987 (Box 38, Folder 19)
    - Environmental Health and Safety Service for the University, 1956-1967 (Box 38, Folder 20)
    - Environmental Health in Schools of Public Health, 1981 (Box 38, Folder 21)
    - Environmental Health Research, 1977 (Box 38, Folder 22)
    - Environmental Sanitation Teaching, 1952-1968 (Box 38, Folder 23)
    - Environmental Studies, 1980 (Box 38, Folder 24)
    - Epidemiology n Environmental Health, 1987 (Box 38, Folder 25)
    - Evaluation in the Management Training Programs of the Department of Health of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, 1967 (Box 38, Folder 26)
    - Executive Committee, 1970-1975 (Box 38, Folder 27)
    - Faculty, 1976 (Box 38, Folder 28)
    - Faculty By-Laws, 1979-1981 (Box 38, Folder 29)
    - Faculty Senate, 1988 (Box 38, Folder 30)
    - Graduate Program in Public Health Engineering, 1949-1990 (Box 38, Folder 31)
    - Graduate School of Public Health history, 1966-1981 (Box 38, Folder 32)
    - Graduate School of Public Health photo, undated (Box 38, Folder 33)
    - Handbook of Teaching Services, 1981-1982 (Box 38, Folder 34)
    - Hatch, Theodore, 1963-1986 (Box 38, Folder 35)
    - Health Services Administration, 1974-1975 (Box 38, Folder 36)
    - Health Status Seminar, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 37)
    - Industrial Environmental Health Sciences, 1979-1980 (Box 38, Folder 38)
    - Keleti, Georg, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 39)
    - Memos, 1980-1999 (Box 38, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1992 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Non-Ingestion Exposures to Contaminants of Potable Water, 1985 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Notes, undated (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Noweir, Madbuli, 1962-1964 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Occupational Safety and Health Education Resource Center, 1977-1978 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Physical Environment: School of Health, 1949-1990 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Posvar, Wesley, 1990 (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Preventive Health Program, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Public Health Service, 1982 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Reports, 1989 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Research Proposals, 1980-1982 (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - Self-Evaluation Steering Committee, 1979 (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - Senate Council, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - Social science, 1964-1983 (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - Solid Waste Committee, 1974-1990 (Box 39, Folder 15)
    - Stone, Donald C., 1971-1972 (Box 39, Folder 16)
    - Undergraduate Studies in Environmental Science, undated (Box 39, Folder 17)
    - Urban and Regional Planning, 1974-1975 (Box 39, Folder 18)
    - Work plans, 1968-1988 (Box 39, Folder 19)
    - Workshops, 1984-1985 (Box 39, Folder 20)
  - Course Material, 1946-1993; 2.
    - Anthropology 1787, 1993 (Box 39, Folder 21)
    - Course development, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 22)
    - Environmental Health 212, 1975-1976 (Box 39, Folder 23)
    - Environmental Health 216, 1965-1977 (Box 39, Folder 24)
    - Environmental Health 217, 1975-1976 (Box 39, Folder 25-26)
    - Environmental Health 225, 1966-1968 (Box 39, Folder 27)
    - Environmental Health 247, 1964-1965 (Box 39, Folder 28)
    - Environmental Health 260, 1969-1970 (Box 39, Folder 29)
    - Environmental Health 266, 1972-1977 (Box 39, Folder 30)
    - Environmental Health 275, undated (Box 39, Folder 31)
    - Environmental Studies, 1981-1986 (Box 39, Folder 32)
    - Environmental and Occupational Health 2510, 1991 (Box 39, Folder 33)
    - Film List for Urban Environmental Health Planning, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 34)
    - Health Services Administration 201, 1972-1975 (Box 39, Folder 35)
    - Health Services Administration 252, 1986 (Box 39, Folder 36)
    - Industrial and Environmental Health Science 231, 1950-1984 (Box 39, Folder 37-38)
    - Industrial and Environmental Health Science 238, 1979 (Box 39, Folder 39)
    - Industrial and Environmental Health Science 239, 1979 (Box 39, Folder 40)
    - Industrial and Environmental Health Science 241, 1982 (Box 39, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 39, Folder 42)
    - Public Health 203, 1957-1959 (Box 39, Folder 43)
    - Public Health 203, 1959 (Box 39, Folder 44)
    - Public Health 213, 1971-1980 (Box 39, Folder 45)
    - Public Health 213, 1971-1980 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Public Health Practice 30, 1952 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Public Health Practice 214, 1969 (Box 40, Folder 3-5)
    - Public Health Practice 215, 1970-1971 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Principles of Environmental Sanitation at North Carolina, 1946 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Selected bibliography on manpower, 1970 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Water supply and water pollution control readings, undated (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Presentations and Publications, 1957-1991; 3.
    - "Adult Mortality in Two Communities with Widely Different Air Pollution Levels", 1976 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - "Assessment of the Influence on Environmental Lead", 1982 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - "Calculation of MAC of Radioactivity", 1957 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - "Comprehensive Report: Determination of Organic Matter in Water", 1964 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - "The Education of Sanitary Engineers in Latin America", 1958 (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - "Environmental Chemistry", 1986 (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - "Environmental Control in the Workplace: Water, Food, Wastes, Rodents", 1991 (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - "Experimental Evaluation of Coal Conversion Solid Waste Residuals: Progress Report", 1979 (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - "Final Evaluation of PETC Coal Conversion Solid and Hazardous Wastes", 1979 (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - "Las Funciones de los Servicios y Organismos de Salud en Relacion con la Vivienda", 1963 (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - "The Gray Area Dilemma: A Study of Attitudes Toward Housing", 1965 (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - "The Health Component of Pollution Control", 1980 (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - "Health Effects of Coal Conversion By-Products in Drinking Water", 1980 (Box 40, Folder 22-23)
    - "Herbert E. Stokinger Lecture", 1979 (Box 40, Folder 24)
    - "Identification and Evaluation of Environmental Health Hazards", 1968 (Box 40, Folder 25)
    - "Industrial Sanitation", 1958 (Box 40, Folder 26)
    - "Infrastructural Development: Impacts on the Environment", 1985 (Box 40, Folder 27)
    - "Intensive Study of the Water at Critical Points on the Monongahela, Allegheny and Ohio Rivers in the Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania Area", 1967 (Box 40, Folder 28)
    - "Keeping It Clean: Controlling the Quality of our Water", undated (Box 40, Folder 29)
    - "Laboratory Short Course for Treatment Plant Operators", 1960 (Box 40, Folder 30)
    - "Legionella and the Environment", 1987 (Box 40, Folder 31)
    - "Master Plan for Water Supply: Accra Tema Metropolitan Area", 1966 (Box 40, Folder 32)
    - "Physiological Aspects of Water Quality", 1961 (Box 40, Folder 33)
    - "Preliminary Study of the Environmental Impacts from Processing and Disposal of Diapers", 1971 (Box 40, Folder 34)
    - "The Problem of Water Pollution", 1971-1984 (Box 40, Folder 35)
    - "Public Health Aspects of Emerging Urban and Suburban Problems", 1962 (Box 40, Folder 36)
    - "Radioactive Waste Disposal in the Upper Ohio River Basin", 1962 (Box 40, Folder 37)
    - "The Role of Free-Living Amoebae Occurring in Heated Effluents as Causative Agents of Human Disease", 1982 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - "Science and Technology: Legacies of the Past and Hope for the Future", 1967 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - "Some factors in the importance in evaluating sites for nuclear industry as determined by a limnological study of the upper Ohio River", 1964 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - "Statement: Hearing on Drinking Water Quality", undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - "Tracer studies with rhodamine-B in a 3.2 kilometer reach of the upper Ohio River", 1964 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - "Water Quality and Cardiovascular Disease", 1970 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - "Westernport Bay Revisited", 1980s (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Student Papers, 1956-1989; 4.
    - "Advances in Wastewater Disinfection Technology", 1985 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - "Air Pollution in Los Angeles County", undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - "Comprehensive Examination", 1963 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - "CPM in Administrative Programs", 1969 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - "Current Consensus: Water Quality and Wastewater Disposal", 1979 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - "Evolution of Federal Pollution Control Policy 1948-1967", 1970 (Box 41, Folder 13-14)
    - "An Examination and Evaluation of Aerobic Sludge Digestion", 1970 (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - "Exposure of Insulation Workers to Total Suspended Particulate Matter and Airborne Glass Fibers", 1979 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - "FICA- The avoidance of a false, partial understanding", 1975 (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - "Home Injury Prevention Awareness", 1989 (Box 41, Folder 18)
    - "Impact of Drought on Water Resources Management in Senegal: The Senegal River Basin", 1988 (Box 41, Folder 19)
    - "Individual Small Systems", 1985 (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - "Investigation of the Effectiveness of the Activated Sludge Process for Giardia Lamblia Cyst Removal", 1988 (Box 41, Folder 21)
    - "A Multivariate Analysis of the Incidence of Elevated Blood Lead Level in Children", 1979 (Box 41, Folder 22)
    - "Petrochemical Contamination of the Valencia Groundwater Supply", 1983 (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - "The Problem of Housing in Jordan: Implications on the Local and National Level", 1969 (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - "Removal of Giardia Lamblia Cysts from Surface Water through the Coagulation-Sedimentation Process", 1987 (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - "Some Chemical Parameters of the Degradation of a Synthetic Organic Pesticide (DDT) in Water", 1963 (Box 41, Folder 26)
    - Term papers: Environmental Health 211, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 27)
    - Term papers: Environmental Health 225, undated (Box 41, Folder 28)
    - Term papers: Environmental Health 266, 1971 (Box 41, Folder 29)
    - "Toxicity of Fluorides to Aquatic Organisms: Modeling for Water Hardness and Temperature", 1985 (Box 41, Folder 30)
    - "The Use of Mechanical Principles in the Evaluation of a Human Functional Dimension", 1956 (Box 41, Folder 31)
    - "A 1974 Study of Water Quality in Twenty-Four Municipal Water Utilities in Allegheny County, Pennsylvania", 1975 (Box 41, Folder 32)
- Audio and Visual Materials, 1979-1985; VI.
  The Audio and Visual Materials Series contains primarily audio cassette recordings of conference proceedings from an unidentified March 1979 environmental sanitation conference. Also included is an audio recording of a Water Workshop in 1985, and slides on assorted topics and Municipal Sewage Treatment. The collection includes material from 1979 and 1985, and the slides are undated.
  - Conference recordings, Tape 1, March 19, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 1)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 2, March 19, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 2)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 3, March 19, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 3)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 4, March 19, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 4)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 5, March 19, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 5)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 6, March 20, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 6)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 7, March 20, 1979 (Box 42, Tape 7)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 8, March 20, 1979 (Box 43, Tape 1)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 9, March 20, 1979 (Box 43, Tape 2)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 10, March 20-21, 1979 (Box 43, Tape 3)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 11, March 21, 1979 (Box 43, Tape 4)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 12, March 21, 1979 (Box 43, Tape 5)
  - Conference recordings, Tape 13, March 21, 1979 (Box 43, Tape 6)
  - Water Workshop, April 24, 1985 (Box 43, Tape 7)
  - Slide box, Assorted topics, undated (Box 42)
  - Slide box, Municipal Sewage Treatment slides, undated (Box 43)